Guide to the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection 2014-2017
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Alfred Haunold was born in Austria in 1929, where he spent his teenage years fond of science, especially botany. He attended a prep school for agricultural studies and graduated from the Agricultural University of Vienna; he earned his doctorate in plant production and wheat breeding in 1951. He obtained a Fulbright scholarship to work on wheat breeding and genetics at the University of Nebraska; after a brief return to Austria, Haunold came back to Nebraska, where he obtained an American PhD and married. He accepted a hop research position in the USDA offices in 1965, despite not being trained as a hop researcher. Soon Haunold found himself in charge of the breeding program after Stanley Brooks resigned. This position as a hop breeder defined the rest of Haunold's career. Haunold's team released the Cascade in 1972, a hop that changed the hops and brewing industries. Haunold had a solid research team, including Chemist Stan Likens, Pathologist Jack Horner, Agronomist Chuck Zimmermann, and Agricultural Chemist Gail Nickerson. This group continued to research, release varieties, and publish their findings in a variety of publications. Haunold retired from the USDA in 1995, but continues to be a valued resource for growers, brewers, and researchers.
Lee Hedgmon is a professional and home brewer, as well as a distiller. Hedgmon is a third generation Portlander who grew up in the Woodlawn neighborhood and attended All Saints Catholic School. She graduated from Lincoln High School in 1991 and attended Portland Community College before joining the JobCorps at Tongue Point on the Oregon Coast. She returned to Portland to work at the Red Lion and attended Portland State University, where she earned a B.A. in Women’s Studies in 2003. She travelled to the University of Minnesota for doctoral work in Feminist Pedagogical Theory in 2010, but moved back to Portland before finishing her dissertation; she returned with an interest in fermentation and was an avid home brewer. She soon joined the Oregon Brew Crew, first holding office as the Festival Coordinator, then Volunteer Committee Chairwoman, and then the President (the first woman in that position). Her first professional brewing position was at Coalition Brewing Company in Portland. That job led to many others, including posts at Portland U-Brew, Old Town Brewing Company, Gateway Brewing, Pints Brewing Company, Ground Breaker Brewing and F.H. Steinbart. She started work as a distiller at McMenamins Edgefield in August 2016.
Jessica Just is the Director of Technical Services for Brew Dr. Kombucha in Portland, Oregon. Just grew up in Portland, where she developed an interest in home brewing quite early. She attended Oregon State University (2005-2008) and was one of the first three graduates (first female) from the OSU Fermentation Science program in the Food Science Department (established 1995). She stayed at OSU for graduate school, where she earned her M.S. in Food Science and Technology in 2001. She interned at the St. Michelle Wine Estates from 2001-2002, and then took a job at Scott Laboratories. She moved to London in 2012, where she worked with the local chapter of the Campaign for Real Ale. She moved back to Corvallis to take a job as an academic advisor and instructor for the Fermentation Science program in 2015 and in 2017 moved back to Portland to take a job at Brew Dr. Kombucha.
Jennifer Kent is the brewer at the McMenamins Thompson Brewery and Public House. Kent spent her early childhood in Alaska and Colorado, but moved to Newport, Oregon in elementary school. When she was in high school she got a horse, which occupied a lot of her time; she graduated from Newport High School in 1993. Her mother is an artist, so Kent spent time being creative and exploring art. She moved to Springfield, Oregon before settling in Salem in 1999. After five years in the food service industry, including at the McMenamins Boons Treasury as a line cook and server, she got interested in brewing. Under the mentorship of McMenamins brewer Gary Nance, Kent learned the fundamentals, but also how to experiment to make new creations or variants. She's inspired by foods, spices, flavors, places, and improvisational belly dancing.
Nathan Kirk teaches in Oregon State University's Department of Integrative Biology, specializing in Marine Ecology. He is also a home brewer. Kirk grew up in New York state, where both his parents were teachers. He studied Biological Sciences at State University of New York at Buffalo (B.S. 2003, M.S. 2006); he was a University Honors Scholar and graduated Magna Cum Laude. He moved to Alabama for a doctoral program at Auburn University, studying Biological Sciences and working as both a teaching and research assistant; it was in Alabama that Kirk explored home brewing. He's been a postdoctoral researcher at Oregon State University, focusing on Marine Ecology, since 2013.
Lee Larsen is one of the founders of 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon. Larsen was born and raised in Corvallis, and he grew up exploring the McDonald Research Forest and playing soccer. He and his family lived in Barcelona, Spain while Larsen was in high school, and it was there that he learned more about the European cider culture and industry. He returned to Oregon in 2003 for his senior year at Corvallis High School. He attended Oregon State University, graduating with a degree in Finance in 2008. He and friends Dave Takush and Aaron Sarnoff-Wood started 2 Towns Ciderhouse in 2010.
Sonia Marie Leikam co-owns Leikam Brewing with her husband, but also works full-time at the Oregon Jewish Community Foundation. Leikam grew up in the Bay Area and moved to Portland in 1999 to attend Lewis and Clark College; she graduated in 2003 with degrees in History and Theater. She graduated from Portland State University in 2006 with an M.Ed. in Secondary Teaching and Education. She worked for North Clackamas School District from 2005 to 2006, at Hillsboro High School as a Drama and American Studies teacher, and at St. Mary’s Academy from 2007 to 2010 as the Director of Student Activities. In 2011, she began work at the Oregon Holocaust Resource Center as their Executive Director, in 2012 she earned a Certificate in Holocaust and Related Studies from Georgetown University, and from 2014 to 2015 she was a Carl Wilkens Fellow, a program to end mass atrocities and genocide. She began work at the Oregon Jewish Community Foundation in 2015, the same year she and her husband opened their community supported and certified kosher brewery (the first in Oregon).
Nick Lorenz is the co-founder and co-owner of Nectar Creek Mead in Corvallis, Oregon, which he runs with his brother Philip. Lorenz grew up in Corvallis, where is family was involved with local farming and agriculture; both siblings worked at Denison Farms as teenagers. Beyond farming and food, Lorenz was especially interested in pottery and soccer. He moved to Burlington to attend the University of Vermont, where he studied Ecological Agriculture and played college soccer. Lorenz worked in an apple orchard during summer breaks from college, where he learned to make apple cider and brandy, and as a river raft guide. His brother pursued a college education in Apiculture and Fermentation Science, and ultimately worked in commercial beekeeping, an interest that led both of them to an interest in mead. They opened Nectar Creek in 2012.
Mark McKay is the owner of McKay Farms and is a sixth generation hop farmer; the McKay family came to Oregon from Scotland and Ireland in the 1840s. He was born in Salem, Oregon and grew up in St. Paul, where he attended a Catholic elementary school. McKay took over the farm after graduating from high school. His family has always grown a variety of crops in St. Paul (hops, mint, filberts, grass seed) and McKay expanded into Independence, Oregon. McKay’s left the hop business in the 1970s when prices dropped; McKay and his brother returned to hop farming in the 1990s when Anheuser-Busch was contracting with growers and the market was getting stronger. He farmed with his brother until 2015, when they split the business.
Lisa Morrison co-owns Belmont Station, a bottle shop and pub in Portland. Morrison grew up in Oklahoma, where she loved to read and since in the choir; she moved to Evergreen, Colorado for high school. She attended Colorado State University, graduating with a degree in Technical Journalism. After graduation she worked as a television news reporter and anchor, a career she continued after moving to Portland in 1989, where she worked for KOIN TV. It was at CSU that her interest in imported and local microbrews was sparked, and continued to grow after exploring the rapidly expanding beer culture in Portland. She began home brewing with her husband and joined the Oregon Brew Crew, a large home brew club, where she met well-known brewers, journalists, and people just interested in making their own beer. Soon her personal interest turned into a career when she started offering beer education classes and wrote about beer for local and national publications. She released the book Craft Beers of the Pacific Northwest in 2011. In 2008, she started Beer O'Clock, a weekly commercial radio show on KXL, where she interviewed people from all facets of the brewing community; the show ran through 2015. In 2013, Morrison became the majority owner of Belmont Station.
Gary Nance is the brewer at the McMenamins on Monroe in Corvallis, Oregon. Nancy was born and raised in Oklahoma, and moved to the west coast after college. He started brewing professionally in 1995, working as the assistant brewer at Spencer's Restaurant and Brewhouse in Springfield, where he helped develop Oregon's first certified organic ale in 1998, and worked briefly at Eugene's West Bros. and Steelhead Brewing Company before taking a job at the McMenamins Thompson Brewery and Public House in Salem in August 2002. He transferred to the Monroe Street facility when it opened in 2006.
Gail Nickerson is a former Agricultural Chemist at Oregon State University. Nickerson grew up in Portland, and as a child was interested in science. Told by her high school guidance counselor that she could only be a teacher, she enrolled at Oregon State University as an Education major. She left school and in 1959 started to work as a full-time laboratory technician. Though she began washing equipment, she soon spent more time in the fields and doing high-level Agricultural Chemistry projects, working on many that were immensely important for the global hop industry. After developing an interest in programming and statistics, she completed her undergraduate degree in computer science in 1984. She retired as a Senior Research Assistant in 2003.
Don Norton is the owner of Norton Hop Farm, a small organic hop farm established in Goshen, Oregon in 2008. Norton was born in Eugene, and spent most of his life in the Spencer Creek area where there were large hop farms. His family moved to Oakridge in 1973, where he attended high school. Norton spent most of his working life doing factory work, before buying the farm and starting to grow hops.
Carole Ockert grew up in Ireland and moved to the United States in 1969, settling just south of Seattle. She met and married Karl Ockert, who later became the first brewer at BridgePort Brewing in Portland, and they moved around the west coast before settling in Portland with their twin daughters. Ockert is a Certified Hypnotherapist in Lake Oswego.
Karl Ockert is the Director of Brewery Operations at Deschutes Brewery. Ockert grew up brewing with his mother, though he didn't initially see that as a professional calling. He attended Humbolt State University to pursue a degree in Natural Sciences/Resources, but he changed directions while he was there and transferred to UC Davis to pursue a degree in fermentation. He mainly took oenology classes while he was there, graduating in 1983 and hopeful to get a job with a Pacific Northwest brewery. Unfortunately, the macro brewing industry was still contracting at that time, so he found himself working at Ponzi Vineyards. He was there for one harvest, and soon Dick Ponzi shared his interest in opening a brewery in Portland. They found a building in late 1983 and by April of 1984 Ockert was the first brewer at BridgePort Brewing; he hired Matt Sage as his assistant and stayed until 1990. He took a position at Anheuser Busch in Newark, but only stayed from 1992-1993. He returned to the west coast, briefly working at Nor'Wester with Jim Bernau in 1994, and in Tacoma starting two brewpubs in 1995 and 1996. He returned to BridgePort in 1996, where he stayed in a position as Brew Master and Plant Manager through 2010. He left to work at the Master Brewers Association of America as their Technical Director; during this time he also worked as a professional brewing consultant. He took his job at Deschutes Brewery in 2015.
Sarah Pederson is the owner of Saravesa, a bar, bottle shop, and breweriana showroom in North Portland. Pederson was born in Denver, Colorado and grew up in a small town in Wisconsin. She went to Minneapolis for college, starting with a graphic design major before switching to journalism; eventually, she created her own major in "aural history," which involved listening to sound and looking at communication. She finished college at California State University in Los Angeles as part of national student exchange, and then went to work for a record company doing public relations. Pederson moved to Portland in the early 2000s, working in PR for high tech firms, but also for her friend at Pix, a patisserie and bar. After leaving the tech industry, she explored brewing through home brewing, workshops at the American Brewer's Guild (brewing certificate 2005), and early jobs at the breweries Hair of the Dog and the New Old Lompoc Bar. She opened Saravesa in 2008.
Sybil Perkins is a Graphic Designer, as well as the brand director and a board member for the Pink Boots Society. She grew up in the Eugene/Springfield area, and had an early interest in arts and music. Perkins was also very engaged with community and civil rights at a young age, thanks in large part to her mother; she lived in Philadelphia and New York City, where she had a variety of experiences as an activist. She returned to the West Coast, where she began to home brew and explore jobs in graphic design. She was an adjunct instructor at both Shoreline Community College and Henry Cogswell College, a Graphic Designer at Cascade Bank (2000-2004), and taught at the School of Visual Concepts from 2003 to 2007. She now has her own graphic design company, where most of her clients are from the foods, hospitality, spirits, and brewing industries. She lives in Everett, Washington.
Mellie Pullman is a professor at Portland State University, where she is the Director of the Business of Craft Brewing Program. Pullman grew up in Chicago; after high school she travelled around the country and took classes at The Evergreen State College, where she studied energy systems and alternative energy. She started a master's program at the University of Utah, focusing Operations Management, Marketing, and Mechanical Engineering and earning an M.B.A., M.S., and Ph.D. She was the first female brewmaster in the U.S. when she took a position in 1986 at Schirf Brewing in Park City, Utah. From 2003 to 2006 she worked at Cornell University, teaching classes related to Service Operations Management and Hotel Administration. She's been at Portland State University since 2005, teaching courses related to food supply chain management, forecasting and production, and global supply chain management. In 2013, her research focus shifted from food to beer and she began work as the Director of the Craft Brewing Program, which provides instruction on business operations for beer, spirits, cider, mead, and kombucha.
Joel Rea is the owner of Corvallis Brewing Supply. Rea spent his early life in Kirkland, Washington, and his family moved to Albany, Oregon when he was in elementary school. He did college work in environmental studies at Prescott College (1993-1993) and the fine arts at the University of Oregon (1995-1996). He worked for the Forest Service, but changed careers to open a home brew and bottle shop in 1997. He has held many classes, hosted events, and mentored many home and commercial brewers.
Joy Hoerner Rich is the daughter of Oregon State University hops specialist G.R. Hoerner. She was born in Ithaca, New York when her dad was on staff at Cornell University; the family soon moved to Portland. She spend most of her youth in Corvallis, and her family regularly hosted parties with people in the macro brewing industries (e.g. Bill Blitz). Rich met her husband at OSU and graduated in 1940s with a degree in home economics. After her husband returned from WWII, the couple moved to Roseburg, where Rich ran a private kindergarten; after kindergarten was part of the public school curriculum Rich started an after school program for kids who needed assistance. Rich is also the niece of artists Berta and Elmer Hader, who are noteworthy in the world of children’s literature; Rich wrote a book in 2014 about their work.
Matt Sage has been a brewer, vintner, and hop consultant whose work has contributed to the creation and expansion of many small businesses across the Pacific Northwest. Sage was born in Portland and graduated from Central Catholic High School. Initially interested in biology, while at Evergreen State College he became more interested in agriculture and farming. Later he had a brief stint at a USDA research lab in Yakima, Washington before getting his first winery job at Columbia Winery. He was hired by Karl Ockert as the second employee at BridgePort Brewing in Portland. Sage left BridgePort in 1990 for a position at Cameron Winery in Dundee, Oregon. He worked for the Colorado-based brewpub chain Rock Bottom, helping open both the Denver and Portland locations and working there through 2004 when he returned to a much bigger BridgePort Brewing. In August 2010, Sage joined Indie Hops, a company that supplies craft brewers with hops.
Robyn Schumacher is a brewer at Stoup Brewing in Seattle's Ballard district. Schumacher was born in Billings, Montana and grew up in Spokane. She had early interests in sports, literature, and science, and after graduating from North Central High School in 1991 she moved to Helena, Montana to study biology at Carroll College. Schumacher moved back to Spokane after college to work odd jobs before returning to Montana to work for the forest service; she returned to Washington to attend Eastern Washington University for her teaching license. She spent 13 years teaching high school science before quitting in 2011 to pursue her interest in the restaurant and brewing industries. In 2012, she became a certified cicerone, the first woman in Washington to be certified. After managing a bar in West Seattle, she joined Lara Zahaba and Brad Benson in opening Stoup Brewing in 2013.
Guy Seghetti taught Social Science for Roseburg, Oregon public schools before retiring in 2008. He grew up in Corvallis, Oregon and went to the University of Utah to pursue a degree in Anthropology. He worked as a USDA Hops and Essential Oils lab and agricultural technician at Oregon State University from 1968 to 1977, where he worked with Gail Nickerson and Alfred Haunold. This was a crucial time in hops breeding program with the release of the Cascade and other hops in the 1970s. Seghetti left the program in 1977 to teach in Roseburg.
Thomas Shellhammer is the Nor’Wester Professor of Fermentation Science at Oregon State University, where he runs a lab dedicated to the chemical and sensory analysis of hops. Shellhammer grew up in San Jose, where his father worked as a field biologist studying fire ecology and his mother worked as an arts educator. He earned all three of his advanced degrees from UC Davis: B.S. in Fermentation Science in 1987, M.S. in Food Science in 1989, and Ph.D. in Food Engineering in 1996. He was an Assistant Professor at The Ohio State University from 1997 to 2001 before taking his current position. He has been actively involved in the American Society of Brewing Chemists, Master Brewers Association of the Americas, Institute of Brewing and Distilling, and Institute of Food Technologists.
Larry Sidor is the founder of Crux Fermentation, a brewery in Bend, Oregon. Soda was born in Corvallis, but moved to La Grande when his father became an extension agent for Union County. The family returned to Corvallis and Sidor graduated from Corvallis High School. He graduated from Oregon State University in 1972 with a B.S. in Food Science and a minor in Enology. He took a wine internship, but his first major professional position was at Olympia Brewing Company, where he worked from 1974 to 1997, occupying positions as an Operations Manager and Assistant Brewer. In 1997 he left Olympia to work at S.S. Steiner in Yakima, Washington as a VP for Operations. Sidor left S.S. Steiner in 2003 and for a time had a vineyard in Yakima. He took a position as the Head Brewer for Deschutes Brewing in Bend, Oregon in 2004, a position he held until 2011 when he left to open his own brewery.
Blair Smith is the owner, orchardist, and cider-maker for Apple Outlaw. Smith was born in Seattle, Washington, but grew up in Stockton, California, where the family had moved for his father's job as a Math Professor at the University of the Pacific. Smith stayed in Stockton for college, where he graduated with a Computer Science degree in 1990; he spent the next 20 years as a software engineer in Livermore. In 2003, Smith and his family moved to Applegate, a town in rural Southern Oregon, where they had a property with an old apple orchard. Smith continued to work as a software contractor before switching careers to run an organic orchard and work full-time as a cider-maker. The Smith family sold apples to cider-makers throughout Oregon and began to press their own apple cider for selling at farmers markets and co-ops. In 2013, transitioned from non-alcoholic to hard cider with their first sales of Apple Bandit.
Hilda Stevens owns Bazi Bierbrasserie, a Belgian-style beer taproom and soccer bar in SE Portland. Stevens immigrated from Guatemala when she was 8 years old, living and going to school in The Woodlands (a community north of Houston, Texas). She attended St Mary's University in San Antonio, studying International Business and Marketing. After graduation worked for business and marketing companies; these jobs provided opportunities to travel extensively through the U.S. and internationally. She became a citizen in 1997, and the next year she moved to Portland in 1998, continuing to work for the San Antonio based NCR. With that job she had the change to travel to Europe in 2006, which is where she discovered Belgian beers. During this same period Stevens took night classes at George Fox University in an accelerated M.B.A. program. After the economic downtown and rolling company layoffs, Stevens decided to revisit a graduate school business plan for opening a bar. She began looking for locations in 2010 and opened Bazi in 2011.